A Finding Aid to the Emily Hall Tremaine Papers, 1890-2000, in the Archives of American Art AAA.trememil
Archives of American Art
Emily Hall Tremaine papers
1890-2000
AAA.trememil
Archives of American Art
8.9 Linear feet
The papers of art collector Emily Hall Tremaine measure 8.9 linear feet and date from 1890 to 2000. Found within the papers are biographical materials on the Hall, von Romberg, and Tremaine families, including a sound cassette on the Tremaines; personal correspondence; art collection files, which include inventory binders, records of sales and donations, artist files, exhibition loan files, and reproduction request files; 2 scrapbooks documenting Tremaine’s first marriage to Baron Maximilian von Romberg; and photographs of Tremaine, her family and friends, and works of art from her collection. There are also materials related the 1984 exhibition The Tremaine collection: 20th Century Masters at the Wadsworth Athenaeum, including a video recording of Philip Johnson’s exhibition lecture.
Tremaine, Emily Hall, 1908-1987
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The papers were donated in 2006 by Tremine’s step-grandson, Burton G. Tremaine III.
Related Archival Materials note
Also found in the Archives of American Art is an oral history interview with Emily Hall Tremaine conducted by Paul Cummings, January 24, 1973.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice. Contact Reference Services for more information.
Biographical/Historical note
Art collector Emily Hall Tremaine (1908-1987) lived in New York City and Madison, Connecticut and was known for having assembled one of the most noteworthy collections of post World War II art focused on modernist, pop, and contemporary artists.
Tremaine was born in Butte, Montana to mining executive William Hubbard Hall and his wife, Elizabeth Smith Hall. Her first marriage to Baron Maximilian von Romberg was well publicized in the society pages of the time and ended with the Baron’s death in a plane accident in 1938. Her second marriage to sugar heir Adolph B. Spreckels Jr. ended in divorce in 1940.
While Tremaine collected art in the 1930s, it was not until her 1945 marriage to industrial executive Burton Tremaine that she began acquiring works in earnest. Together, the Tremaines assembled a collection that initially focused on American and European modern artists and would eventually include emerging pop and contemporary art. Their first purchase was Piet Mondrian’s unfinished painting, Victory Boogie Woogie, now owned by the Gemeentemuseum. The collection would eventually number over 400 art works and range from paintings by Picasso, Kandinsky, and Georges Braque to works by Jasper Johns, Claes Oldenburg, Roy Lichtenstein, and Jean-Michel Basquiat. While single pieces were sold, traded, or donated throughout Tremaine's active collecting years, the bulk of the collection was sold at auction in 1988 and 1991 to raise funds for the Emily Hall Tremaine Foundation. Tremaine died from complications of emphysema in 1987.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of art collector Emily Hall Tremaine measure 8.9 linear feet and date from 1890 to 2000. Found within the papers are biographical materials on the Hall, von Romberg, and Tremaine families, including a sound cassette on the Tremaines; personal correspondence; art collection files, which include inventory binders, records of sales and donations, artist files, exhibition loan files, and reproduction request files; 2 scrapbooks documenting Tremaine’s first marriage to Baron Maximilian von Romberg; and photographs of Tremaine, her family and friends, and works of art from her collection. There are also materials related the 1984 exhibition The Tremaine collection: 20th Century Masters at the Wadsworth Athenaeum, including a video recording of Philip Johnson’s exhibition lecture.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 8 series.
Series 1: Biographical Materials, 1910-1980 (7 folders; Box 1)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1905-1985 (0.4 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 3: Art Collection Files, 1950-1980 (0.6 linear feet; Boxes 1, 9)
Series 4: Artist Files, 1936-2000 (4.6 linear feet; Boxes 2-6, 9)
Series 5: Exhibition Loan Files, 1960-2000 (1.5 linear feet; Boxes 6-7)
Series 6: Reproduction Request Files, 1965-1988 (0.6 linear feet; Box 8)
Series 7: Scrapbooks, 1931-1937 (0.3 linear feet; Boxes 9-10)
Series 8: Photographic Materials, 1890-1997 (0.8 linear feet; Boxes 8, 10-11)
Johnson, Philip, 1906-2005; Von Romberg, Maximillian, Baron; Wadsworth Atheneum; Art--Collectors and collecting--California--Interviews; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Sound recordings; Video recordings
- Biographical Materials, 1910-1980; Series 1; 7 Folders Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical materials include a booklet reprinting the letters of Tremaine’s uncle, Horace Hall, biographical information on her grandfather, Stephen Smith, and the banking account book of her father, William Hall. There are also bookplates from Tremaine’s first husband, Baron Maximilian von Romberg; a sound cassette recording documenting the family of her third husband, Burton Tremaine; and an undated watercolor portrait of Emily Hall as a child.
  Arrangement note
  Materials are arranged by document type.
  - Family, Hall, Horace M. (uncle), 1959 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Family, Hall, William H. (father), circa 1910 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Family, Smith, Stephen Morgan (grandfather), circa 1960 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Family, Tremaine, Burton, circa 1970-1980; 1 Sound cassettes Handwritten note on original cassette: "How the Tremaines Got Here First" (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Family, von Romberg, Maximilian, circa 1930-1939 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Watercolor Portrait of Emily Hall, circa 1918-1920 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous, California Residences, circa 1945-1975 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1905-1985; Series 2; 0.4 Linear feet Box 1
  Correspondence includes a number of letters from Tremaine’s mother, Elizabeth Hall, and her sister, Jane Noble, as well as miscellaneous notes and letters from Tremaine’s three husbands, Maximilian von Romberg, Adolph Spreckels, and Burton Tremaine. There are also miscellaneous letters and cards from other family and friends, including reproductions of artwork from Tremaine’s collection that were sent as Christmas cards.
  Materials have retained arrangement by document type and sender.
  - Christmas Cards, Received, circa 1940-1970 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Christmas Cards, Sent, Circa 1960-1985 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Family, circa 1950-1970 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Friends, circa 1950-1970 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Hall, Elizabeth Purdon Smith (mother), circa 1905-1976 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Hall, William Hubbard (father), 1923 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Noble, Jane Hall (sister), circa 1936-1970 (Box 1, Folder 14-15)
  - Spreckels, Adolph B., circa 1939-1944 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Tremaine, Burton, circa 1944-1969 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - von Romberg, Maximilian, circa 1928-1942 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Art Collection Files, 1950-1980; Series 3; 0.6 Linear feet Boxes 1, 9
  Art collection files consists of three inventory binders and an index card file cataloging over 400 pieces of American and European art collected by Tremaine. These documents record dates of purchase, sale prices, insurance and market values, provenance, condition, exhibition loans, and reproductions in publications. The index cards are divided into two sections, paintings sold or donated prior to Tremaine’s death, and works of art remaining in the collection after her death. There are also subject files on Native American art, and primitive and pop art, as well as miscellaneous sale invoices and receipts.
  - Inventory Binder #1, circa 1970-1980 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Inventory Binder #2, circa 1975 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Inventory Binder #3, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Oversized material housed in Box 9, Folder 1.
  - Inventory Index Files, circa 1950-1980 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Paintings sold or donated before Tremaine's death.
  - Inventory Index Files, circa 1950-1980 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Paintings in collection after Tremaine's death.
  - Native American Art, circa 1970-1976 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Pop Art, circa 1960-1970 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Primitive Art, circa 1960-1978 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Miscellaneous Invoices, circa 1960-1975 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Miscellaneous Shipping and Handling, circa 1956-1970 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Oversize Inventory Binder from Box 1, Folder 21, 1979 (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Artist Files, 1936-2000; Series 4; 4.6 Linear feet Boxes 2-6, 9
  Artist Files contain correspondence with artists, galleries, and museums, as well as printed and photographic material documenting works of art in the Tremaine collection. Over 200 artists whose works were purchased, sold, traded, or donated, or whose works were considered for purchase, are included. Artists range from modernists Georges Braque, Paul Klee, Jean Arp, and Marcel Duchamp to pop and contemporary artists such as Andy Warhol, Mark Rothko, Yves Klein, Dan Flavin, Michael Heizer, and Jim Dine. There is also significant research and documentation on the provenance, restoration, and sale of Piet Mondrian’s Victory Boogie Woogie, which was sold in 1988.
  Materials are arranged alphabetically by surname of the artist.
  - Abidine, Dino, circa 1958-1972 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Adam-Tessier, Maxine, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Adams, Robert, 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Agam, Jacob Gipstein, circa 1954 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Albers, Josef, circa 1960-1981 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Alviani, Getulio, 1965-1980 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Amino, Leo, circa 1964 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Andre, Carl, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Andreyev, Milet, circa 1960 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Armitage, Kenneth, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Arp, Jean, circa 1949-1977 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Artschwager, Richard, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Austin, A. Everet, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Austin, Darrel, circa 1960 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Baj, circa 1960 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Baruchello, Gianfranco, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Bell, Larry, circa 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Bertoia, Harry, circa 1960 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Bess, Forest, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Bloom, Miriam, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Blosum, Vern, circa 1960 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Bolotowski, Ilya, circa 1955 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Bontecou, Lee, 1958-1967 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Borja, Eric, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Braque, Georges, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Braque, Georges, 1938-1973 (Box 2, Folder 26-27)
    Information on the work "Black Rose."
  - Bro, Rene Brault, circa 1960 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Bugnob-Sergio, circa 1965 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Burle-Marx, Roberto, 1949-1966 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - C Miscellaneous, circa 1961-1967 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Cage, John, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Calder, Alexander, 1947-1982 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Callery, Mary, 1947-1964 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Carone, Nicholas, circa 1960 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Castro-Cid, Enrique, 1965-1968 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Chamberlain, John, 1960-1982 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Christo, 1965-1984 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Chryssa, circa 1966-1979 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Clemens, Paul, circa 1960 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Corse, Mary, 1971-1980 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Courtin, Pierre, circa 1960 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Cousins, Patty, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Crawford, Ralston, 1950-1977 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - da Silva, Vieira, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Daphnis, Nassos, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Davis, Cecil Clark, 1936-1991 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Davis, Stuart, 1947-1997 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - de Chirico, Georgio, circa 1960 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - de Kooning, Willem, circa 1956-1983 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - de Maria, Walter, 1966-1979 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - de Rivera, Jose, circa 1946-1960 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - de Stael, Nicolas, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Delaunay, Robert, circa 1954-1991 (Box 2, Folder 54-56)
  - DiDonna, Profirio, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Dill, Guy, circa 1974-1978 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Dine, Jim, circa 1962-1985 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Disuvero, Mark, 1963-1973 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Drexler, Rosalind, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Dubuffet, Jean, 1966-1984 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Duchamp, Marcel, 1965-1978 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Duterer, William S., circa 1960-1972 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - E Miscellaneous, circa 1953 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Ernst, Max, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Etnier, Stephen, 1936-1957 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - F Miscellaneous, circa 1955 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Farfa, circa 1960 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Feiler, Paul, circa 1960 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Fievre, Yolande, circa 1960 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Fine, Perle, circa 1960 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Flavin, Dan, circa 1970 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Fontana, Lucio, circa 1960 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Francisco, Richard, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Fuller, Buckminster, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - G Miscellaneous, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Giocometti, Alberto, 1948-1987 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Glasson, Larry, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Griffa, Giorgio, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Gris, Juan, 1947-1991 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Gysin, Brion, circa 1962 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - H Miscellaneous, 1963-1968 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Habbah, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Hague, Raoul, circa 1956 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Heizer, Michael, 1972-1981 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Helion, Jean, 1959-1984 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Hendricks, Geoffrey, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Hennessy, Richard, circa 1965 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Heron, Hilary, circa 1953-1964 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Higgins, Edward, 1960-1961 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Hinman, Charles, 1964-1973 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - I Miscellaneous, circa 1960 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Irwin, Robert, 1966-1981 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - J Miscellaneous, circa 1953-1962 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Jenney, Neil, 1975-1986 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Johns, Jasper, 1964-1988 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Johnson, Philip, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Johnson, Ray, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Jorn, Asger, circa 1960 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Judd, Donald, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - K Miscellaneous, circa 1951 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Kalina, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Kalinowski, Horst Ergon, circa 1965 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Kandinsky, Vassily, 1945-1964 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Kehn, T. Langdon, circa 1960 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Kendrick, Mel, 1983-1985 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Kimura, Kentaro, circa 1960 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Kinley, Peter, circa 1960 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Klee, Paul, 1940-1979 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Klein, Yves, circa 1966-1986 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Kline, Franz, circa 1958-1972 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Komodore, Bill, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Kricke, Norbert, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Kruegar, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Kunisada, circa 1960 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Kuniyoshi, Yasuo, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - L Miscellaneous, circa 1951-1966 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Laing, Gerald, 1966-1979 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Lam, Janette, 1963-1965 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Lapayese, Ramon, circa 1960 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Le Corbusier, 1947-1963 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Leger, Fernand, 1956-1993 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Lewis, Morris, circa 1965 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Lewitt, Sol, 1967-1978 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Liberman, Alexander, 1963-1967 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Lichtenstein, Roy, 1964-1988 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Lipchitz, Jacques, 1948-1968 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Lissitsky, El, circa 1949-1992 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - Littell, Ross, 1970-1983 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Lora, circa 1960 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - M Miscellaneous, circa 1962 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Mangold, Robert, circa 1965 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Manzoni, Piero, 1970-1986 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Marca-Relli, 1959-1962 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Marden, Brice, 1982-1983 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Marin, John, 1947-1987 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Miro, Joan, 1957-1991 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Martin, Agnes, 1972-1981 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Mathieu, Georges A., 1955-1983 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Matisse, 1988-1990 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Matta, 1947-1957 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Meadmore, Clement, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Meadows, Bernard, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Milkowski, Antoni, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Moholy-Nagy, Laszlo, 1947-1957 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Mondrian, Piet, Catalog File, circa 1982 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Mondrian, Piet, Correspondence, circa 1945-1998 (Box 4, Folder 21-26)
  - Mondrian, Piet, Perle Fine, circa 1946-1950 (Box 4, Folder 27-30)
    Includes correspondence, explanatory charts, writings, and photographs of work by Perle Fine. Oversized materials housed in Box 9, Folder 2.
  - Mondrian, Piet, Writings, circa 1942-1984 (Box 4, Folder 31-35)
  - Mondrian, Piet, Printed Material, circa 1945-1985 (Box 4, Folder 36-39)
  - Mondrian, Piet, Printed Material, 1944-1986 (Box 5, Folder 1-4)
    Oversized material housed in Box 9, Folder 2.
  - Mondrian, Piet, Photographic Materials, circa 1950-1980 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Moore, Henry, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Mortimer, Barbara, circa 1965 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Moscowitz, Robert, circa 1965 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Motherwell, Robert, circa 1965 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Nevelson, Louise, circa 1960-1991 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Newman, Barnett, 1948-1988 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Newmann, Robert, 1970-1978 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Nicholson, Ben, 1949-1959 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Noel, Georges, circa 1960 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Ohlson, Doug, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - O'Keefe, Georgia, circa 1977-1986 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Oldenburg, Claes, 1960-1985 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Parsons, Betty, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Peire, Luc, 1960-1962 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Pereira, Irene Rice, circa 1965 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Pereira, Marilyn, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Phillips, Gifford, circa 1966 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Philolaos, 1963-1978 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Picasso, Pablo, 1947-1964 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Pistoletto, 1964-1981 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Pollock, Jackson, circa 1956-1982 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Pomodoro, Arnaldo, 1970-1975 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Poons, Larry, 1963-1965 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Porter, Stephen, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Rabkin, Leo, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Ramos, Mel, circa 1960 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Rauschenberg, Robert, 1958-1968 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Ray, Man, 1965-1966 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Rayo, Omar, circa 1965-1968 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Reinhart, Ad, 1960-1967 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Riley, Bridget, 1965-1970 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Riopelle, Jean Paul, 1952-1954 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Robbins, Bruce, circa 1976-1984 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Rockburne, Dorothea, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Rohm, Robert, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Romero, Orozco, circa 1960 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Rosenquist, James, 1961-1985 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Roth, Diter, circa 1965 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Rothko, Mark, circa 1953-1976 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Ryman, Robert, 1967-1973 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Samaras, Lucas, 1966-1986 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Scarpitta, Salvadore, circa 1960 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Scharl, Joseph, circa 1960 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Schwarz, Arthur, circa 1961-1967 (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Schwitters, Kurt, 1948-1998 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Seawright, James, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Sekula, Sonia, circa 1964 (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Serra, Richard, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Seuphor, Michael, 1953-1975 (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Shedletsky, Stuart, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Sheeler, Charles, circa 1960 (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - Smith, Richard, 1966-1982 (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - Smith, Tony, 1967-1986 (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - Soto, Jesus Raphael, circa 1960 (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - Soulages, Pierre, 1955-1956 (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - Stamos, Theodoros, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - Stankiewicz, Richard, 1962-1978 (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - Stanley, Bob, 1965-1972 (Box 5, Folder 63)
  - Stark, Jack Gage, circa 1965 (Box 5, Folder 64)
  - Stella, Frank, circa 1960-1985 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Stout, Myron, 1962-1979 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Strider, Marjorie, 1965-1984 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Sturtevant, Elaine, 1961 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Sutherland, Graham, circa 1960 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Takis, circa 1960 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Talman, Paul, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Tauber-Arp, Sophie, circa 1960 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Taubes, circa 1965 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Thornton, Leslie, 1956-1960 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Tinguely, Jean, 1961 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Tobey, Mark, 1944 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Tomasello, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Trova, Ernest, circa 1963-1971 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Tsingos, Thanos, circa 1960 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Tunnard, John, circa 1960 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Tuttle, Richard, 1965-1984 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Valenta, Barbara, 1977-1983 (Box 6, Folder 18-19)
  - Van Doesburg, Theo, circa 1947-1982 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Van Hoeydock, circa 1965 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Vasarelly, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Vasey, Steve, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Vollmer, Ruth, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Warhol, Andy, circa 1962-2000 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Wells, Cady, circa 1965 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Wesselman, Tom, 1961-1979 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Williams, Neil, circa 1981 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Yrisarry, Mario, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Zakanych, Robert, 1968-1969 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Oversize Piet Mondrian Charts and Periodical from Box 4, Folder 28 and Box 5, Folder 2, 1946-1974 (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Exhibition Loan Files, 1960-2000; Series 5; 1.5 Linear feet Boxes 6-7
  Exhibition loan files consist of correspondence, lists, forms/invoices, and printed and photographic material tracking works of art from the Tremaine collection loaned for museum and gallery exhibitions. There are also extensive files documenting the 1984 exhibition of close to 150 works from the Tremaine collection organized by the Wadsworth Atheneum, including a video lecture by Philip Johnson.
  Materials are arranged chronologically according to the year works of art were returned to the collection.
  - Chronological, 1960-1965 (Box 6, Folder 31-38)
  - Chronological, 1966-1970 (Box 6, Folder 39-44)
  - Chronological, 1971-1979 (Box 7, Folder 1-10)
  - Chronological, 1980-1987; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) Includes transcript. Handwritten note on original cassette: "Philip Johnson - Feb. 25, 1984 Wadsworth Atheneum" (Box 7, Folder 11-21)
  - Chronological, 1991, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 22-23)
- Reproduction Request Files, 1965-1988; Series 6; 0.6 Linear feet Box 8
  Reproduction request files consist of correspondence, forms/invoices, and printed and photographic material tracking works of art from the Tremaine collection published in exhibition catalogs, periodicals, and newspapers.
  Materials are arranged chronologically and filed by year of reproduction request.
  - Ectachromes or Color Transparencies, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Request for Photos, circa 1965-1966 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Chronological, 1965-1976 (Box 8, Folder 3-9)
  - Chronological, 1977-1988 (Box 8, Folder 10-19)
- Scrapbooks, 1931-1937; Series 7; 0.3 Linear feet Boxes 9-10
  The two scrapbooks consist of newspaper clippings and photographs documenting news of the courtship and marriage of Emily Hall to her first husband, Baron Maximilian von Romberg.
  Materials are arranged chronologically.
  - Scrapbook #1, circa 1935-1936 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook #2, 1931-1937 (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Photographic Materials, 1890-1997; Series 8; 0.8 Linear feet Boxes 8, 10-11